<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, preached at Edinburgh in the Parliament-House, November 17th, 1700, before his Grace, James, Duke of Queensberry, his Majesties High Commissioner; and many of the nobility, barrons, burrows, members of the High Court of Parliament, / by David Williamson minister of the Gospel, at West-Kirk.</title>
            <author>Williamson, David, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2797B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529115</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179273</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06642)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179273)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2781:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, preached at Edinburgh in the Parliament-House, November 17th, 1700, before his Grace, James, Duke of Queensberry, his Majesties High Commissioner; and many of the nobility, barrons, burrows, members of the High Court of Parliament, / by David Williamson minister of the Gospel, at West-Kirk.</title>
                  <author>Williamson, David, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3-24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Mosman, and are to be sold at his shop in the Parliament-Clos,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Government --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XIX, 41-42 --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah I, 3 --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179273:1"/>
            <p>A Sermon, Preached at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in the <hi>Parliament-Houſe. November 17th.</hi> 1700 Before His <hi>GRACE,</hi> JAMES, Duke of <hi>Queensberry,</hi> HIS MAJESTIES HIGH COMMISSIONER; AND Many of the <hi>Nobility, Barrons, Burrows,</hi> Members of the High Court of PARLIAMENT, BY <hi>David Williamſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, at <hi>Weſt-Kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Moſman,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop in the <hi>Parliament-Cloſs,</hi> in the Year 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179273:2"/>
            <head>Good Reader,</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Author being urged, by ſeveral Perſons of Honour and others, To Print his Sermon, found it neceſſar to add a few things, He intended to have delivered; but was prevented by a miſtake of the Time.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179273:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE before Prayer</head>
            <p>I would ſpeak that word to this honourable Aſſembly, which <hi>Paul</hi> hath <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 1 <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>My hearts deſire and prayer to God for you all, is that you may be ſaved,</hi> could I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain onething of theſe preſent, to believe that there is a God, and that the Scriptures are the Truth and Word of God;</q> I would hope this ſhould not be a loſt but bleſſed occaſion. I have charity towards the moſt part, but fears of ſome; For there is no age wherein <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Prophanity</hi> have been more rife, than in this of our time: Many ſaying in their hearts, with the Fool, <hi>there is no God Pſal</hi> 14, verſe 1. their corrupt and abominable Practices ſay, <hi>the fear of God is not before their eyes:</hi> Their folly will be reproved, when they feel what they fear not. We muſt not ſhun to tell you Gods mind from his Word, which you would notice with Reverence, for by this word you muſt be all judged at the laſt Day. <hi>John</hi> 12 48. The Prophet ſayeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 46. <q rend="inline">I will ſpeak of thy Teſtimonies alſo before Kings and not be aſhamed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> I will tell yow what Binds us, God ſends <hi>Jerimiah</hi> to Great Men. and ſayeth <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.8 17. be not afraid of their faces for <hi>I</hi> will be with thee to deliver thee ſayeth the Lord. Be not diſmaid at their faces; leaſt I confound thee before them. I knowe not what the deſign of all may be in coming here; but I have heard, I have read, <hi>I</hi> have known in experience ſome come to hear a Preaching who might have been ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Preaching proof, and to have no good deſign, curioſitie the beſt of it, and God faſtned a nail of conviction in their Conſciences, and they could never looſe the Grip, what the Lord will do this day, I know not, but if the Lord would lay his word in about all your hearts, it might give a lift to the intereſts both of Church and ſtate, and God even our God might dwell amongſt us and bleſs us, and our Land yeild her increaſe. Be ware of drowſines lightneſs and wandering, and let us call on God for his Countenance bleſſing and aſſiſtance.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <head>A SERMON on</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 19.41.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>And when he was come near, he beheld the City, and wept over it.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>42.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>Saying, If thou hadst known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy Peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 1.3.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>The Ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib: But Iſrael doth not know, my people doeth not conſider.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I intend not to be tedious in Introduction. Explication, or Diviſion of the Words nor curious in Method, but to offer a few plain Truths; Both the Prophet and our Saviour ſpeaks to the Rulers, and the people ruled, <hi>Iſatah:</hi> 9, 16. <hi>The Leaders of this people cauſe them to err, and they that are led of them are deſtroyed,</hi> and our Saviour ſays <hi>Matth.</hi> 15, 14. <hi>The blind are Leaders of the blind, and both ſhall fall into the Ditch.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iaſiah:</hi> in verſe 2d directs his Speech to the ſenſelcis Creatures, <hi>(hear O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and give car O Earth,</hi> The more to awaken and affect the <hi>Iſrelites,</hi> his covenanted and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179273:3"/>profeſſed people, he challenges them as below the dullneſs of Bruites, that acknowledge and obey their Owners who provides them, and in their Way ſhews reſpect to their maſters but my people <hi>Iſrael</hi> are more ſtupid than bruites; they do not own nor acknowledge me. There is a ſort of people in this Generation, called <hi>Deiſts,</hi> but I call them <hi>Aitheists,</hi> who arrogat the name of <hi>Witt's</hi> they cry down revealed Religion, deſpiſe their Souls, refuſe Inſtruction, reject a Saviour, and deny future Rewards and Puniſhments, They live like Beaſts, and are worſe than Beaſts, they do not own and reverence their Maſter; And <hi>I</hi> may ſay are worſe then Devils, <hi>Jam:</hi> 2, 19. <hi>They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and tremble;</hi> It may be many here never beleived, never trembled.</p>
            <p>In that Text of <hi>Luke,</hi> our Lord foreſeeing the woful day of Deſolation coming u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> was affectionatly concerned with their deplorable condition, and wept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them. And breaks out in this abrupt and emphatick Speech, <hi>If thou even thou hadeſt known, or O that thou hadſt known, or happy had thou been if thou hadeſt known in this thy day, Id eſt</hi> that is the time of his preaching to them which they ſlighted; they ſhut their eyes, and God Judicially plagued them with blindneſs. To know fignifies here, to acknowledge, bend the Mind, lay to heart, and improve for practice. By things belonging to their peace is underſtood, things that belong both to their hapineſs inward and outward Their peace with God, peace in their Conſciences, and peace with the Creatures</p>
            <p>There be five things in thir words. 1 That there are ſome things that belong to a peoples peace, in all theſe reſpects. 2dly That we are bound to ſtudy a heart affecting knowledge of theſe things. 3dly That the preſent time and day would be thus improven. 4tly The advantage that redounds to theſe that thus improve time. It would prevent Miſery. It is implyed that people ſmart for neglect of time. 5tly. Slighting time, loſſing the ſeaſon, may never be recovered again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctrine.</hi> The point I offer is this, That it is the Intereſt of all who would be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven of God and their own Conſciences; and eſcape a challenge and Ruine, to know and take to heart the things that belong to their peace, to their Souls peace, the peace of the Church and Land. I will not inſiſt to prove ſo evident a point. I ſhall firſt ſpeake a Word of Gods Peace, which is the Spring of all other true Peace. 2dly Of theſe thing to be known, that belongs to the Souls peace, to the peace of a Church and Land.</p>
            <p>For the Peace of God I give theſe 6 Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 it is not common to all, Its Chriſts Gift and Legacy, to His peculiar people, <hi>John</hi> 14, 27. <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you.</hi> 2dly It is the purchaſe of Chriſts Blood, <hi>Ephes:</hi> 2d 13 14. Ye are made near by the Blood of Chriſt. for He is our peace. 3dly It is a ſure peace, <hi>Iſiah</hi> 54 10 <hi>The Covenant of my peace ſhall never be removed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord.</hi> 4tly. It guards the Believers heart and Mind in all caſes. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. 5tly Its the great end and errand of the Miniſtry, 2 <hi>Corinth</hi> 5 20 <hi>We are Embaſsaaors for Chriſt as though God, did beſeech you by us we pray you in Christs stead be ye reconeiled to God.</hi> 6tly. They make a good Teſtament at Death, who are found with him in peace at his Appearing.</p>
            <p>It is a precious peace, prize it highly,i We may not want it, nor can we ſtand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lords fade, be tender of it and afraid to looſe the ſenſe of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly I come to ſpeak of things that belong to your peace, that ye are to ſtudy the heart affecting knowledge off.</p>
            <p>And 1st. What belongs to your Souls peace as Chriſtians, 2dly. What belongs to the Churches and Lands peace.</p>
            <p>I begin with that, What belongs to the Peace of Believers as Chriſtians: For if ye
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179273:3"/>be good Chriſtians, ye will be the better Rulers. I confeſs the Soveraign Lord, can make the Earth help the Woman. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16. Men of Earthly and Senſual Minds and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, but theſe will not be faſt Freinds, when the Wind blows in an oth erairt they alter <hi>Jehu</hi> made his Zeal a ſtirrop to mount the Throne.</p>
            <p>I give you account of theſe things, That ye would ſtudy Haeart-affecting practical. knowledge of, in order to your Peace.</p>
            <p>I offer you Ten Heads here.</p>
            <p>You muſt know God. 1. That he is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>He that comes to God muſt believe that he is;</hi> This is the Fountain of all true Knowledge, and the Spring of all true Peace and Comfort. 2ly. That we muſt know what He is, what is His Name, what the the Word declares Him to be, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſays, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18. <hi>I beſeech thee ſhew me thy Glory</hi> And the Lord proclaims His Name, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>The LORD, the LORD GOD, merciful and gracious, long ſuffering, and aboundant in goodneſs and Truth. Keeping Mercy for thouſands, forgiving Iniquity, Tranſgreſſion and Sin, and that will by no means clear the guilty.</hi> O what advantage redounds from this, it relates to our Peace, and the right ordering of our Spirits, And making the Stream of our Affections run in the right Channel; To know Him in His Infinite Excellent and Glorious Perfections, They that know His Name faithful and true, will put their Truſt in Him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. If we knew Him in His Holineſs, Power, Juſtice, and Love, then ſhould we readily Fear, Love, and Obey Him; If we knew Him in His Goodneſs and Mercy, it would draw out our deſires and delight after him, If we knew Him in His Soveraignity, then ſhould we acquieſce in all his diſpoſings of our lote: If we knew Him in His Omniſciency, that would keep our Hearts in aw: All theſe relate to our Peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. <hi>Head,</hi> We muſt ſtudy to know Chriſt, if we regaird our Peace; And firſt in the Statelyneſs of His Perſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>who is the brightneſs of the Fathers Glory, the expreſs Image of his Perſon,</hi> This is a ſweet conſideration, that we have ſuch a Noble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It relates to our Peace to know him in his Natures, God, Man, a meek Mediator to deal between God and Man.</p>
            <p>To know Him in His Human Nature, Fleſh of our Fleſh and Bone of our Bone, our God who has right to redeem, and has payed our Debt in our Nature, he has dignified our Nature, in aſſuming our Nature to a perſonal Union, with his God-head, he will never lay it down again <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24. <hi>This Man continueth ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then we muſt know him in his Divine Nature <hi>Iſah</hi> 7.14. <hi>Immanuel</hi> the Mighty God <hi>Iſah</hi> 9.6. I have laid your help ſayeth the Lord upon one that is Mighty <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.19 he trode the <hi>Wine Preſs</hi> of his Fathers wrath alone, and ſpeaks in Righteouſnes mighty to ſave <hi>Iſah</hi> 63.2.3. His God-head ſuſtaind the human nature, that he ſunk not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſufferings, and gives an infinite meriting value to his ſufferings by vertue of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head he roſe from the deed <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt know him in his name, which is as an oyntment poured forth <hi>Cano:</hi> 13: The Lord Jeſus Chriſt, every letter ſweeter than another Lord of Lords King of Kings <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. This is a Quieting conſideration, when we have many Lords who would impoſe on our Conſciences, we have one Lord and Law-giver <hi>James</hi> 4.12. No Law can bind the Conſcience but what is conſonant to his Law. Jeſus O but that has a ſweet ſound to a ſenſible loſt Sinner. he gets his name from his earrand, thou ſhalt call his name Jeſus ſaid the Anegl, for he ſhall ſave his People from their Sins thus he is the Prince of Peace, <hi>Iſaih</hi> 9.6. Chriſt <hi>ideſt</hi> anointed. it firſt imports he was Gods choiſe for a Saviour <hi>Iſah.</hi> 42.1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my ſervant whom I uphold, mine Elect in whom my Soul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179273:4"/>God never ſpoke ſuch a word of another, then it imports he was well furniſhed for all his Offices anointed with the <hi>Oyl</hi> of joy above his Fellows <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7 Full of Grace and Truth, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. Having the fulneſs of the God-head dwelling in him bodily, <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 2.9. Holy Angels, have a fulneſs of ſufficiency, enough of Grace to ſerve themſelves, but non to ſpare but Chriſt hath a fulneſs of redundancy, a running over fulneſs, for as many as have been at the Wells of Salvation <hi>Iſah.</hi> 12.3. Theſe Five Thouſand Years and more the Well is, as full now as ever, his fulneſs being infinite it can not be deminiſhed. 4ly We muſt know him in his Offices 1st. As the Anointed Well qualified Prophet who has compaſſion on the ignorant <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2. And inſtructs with a ſtrong hand, <hi>Iſah.</hi> 8 11. We have weak hands, he is meek and lowly in heart <hi>Math.</hi> 11.29. We need not ſcar: to learn of him, he has all the Treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge, <hi>Coloſ</hi> 2.3. He has the tongue of the Learned, to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to a weary Soul <hi>Iſah.</hi> 50.4. he leads the blind by a way they know not, Makes darkneſs light befor them, <hi>Iſah.</hi> 42.16. he has a prerogative that non els can pretend to he teaches his People to profit gives an Ingine and capacity to take up the Leſſon, <hi>Iſah.</hi> 48.17. he is the Maſter of Aſſemblies that faſtens the nail in a ſure place <hi>Eccie;</hi> 12.11. Then ſecondly We muſt know him in his Prieſtly Office 1. as to his ſatisfaction who has payed a competent price for our Ranſom 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2.6. he has obtained a diſcharge, In ſign and token whereof it is ſaid <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24. he dyed, for our ſins to pay our debt and roſe for our Righteouſneſs. to prove the payment was accepted and accompts cleared elſe he had not got out of Priſon, thus Gods Righteouſneſs is declared, that he is juſt to juſtifie them that believe in Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26. having gotten payment of the Cautioner, he will note rave it overagain at the Beleivers hands. O What a cordial is this, to theſe weighted with the ſenſe of guilt. Then as to his Interceſſion, we have a freind in Heaven before us who is called the Angel, have ing a Golden Cenſure with much incenſe that he ſhould offer it with the Prayers of all Saints upon the Golden-Alter which is befor the Throne <hi>Revel.</hi> 8.3. He Compears be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for God for us, when Law, Satan, and Conſcience, accuſe, he riſes up and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears for the poor Sinner to anſwear what can be charged upon him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24 And this is ſweet that he never loſed a cauſe he took in hand <hi>John</hi> 11.42, The Father hears him always he was never denyed a ſute. Then we ſhould know him in his Kingly Office a Glorious King <hi>Pſal</hi> 24.7. who choiſes the Officers of his own houſe <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.-11. 12 he ſubdues and captivats Souls to his obedience <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.4.5. he rules by his Word and Spirit and defends by his power, and can daſh the Pot-Shards in pieces that are his Enemies, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.9. We moſt receive whole Chriſt in all his Offices, if we be not ruled by his Law, we cannot be ſaved by his death, Some will not have this Man to reign over them. <hi>Luke.</hi> 19.14. 5ly we muſt know him in his Love 1ſt in the freedom of it. We have nothing to engage his love, but much in us to provock his Loathing. He loved <hi>Jacob</hi> freely <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.14. 2ly. The ſpeciallity of this Love in two reſpects 1ſt. in reſpect of the kind. Men choſen and loved, no fallen Angels <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. <hi>he took not on him the nature of Angels,</hi> their execution was as quick as their fall caſt out of favour for ever. 2ly. in reſpect that he makes a choice among fallen Men and loves not all alike all-though all be of the ſame maſs. This makes every Beleiver a wonder to himſelf and to ſay what wonder he made choiſe of me, 3ly in the antiquity of it, from everlaſting. every Beleiver is the birth of eternal love before he made the Earth or the World; or laid the foundations thereof his delights were with the Sons of Men <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.29. &amp;c. then in the duration of it his mercy and love is everlaſting <hi>Pſ</hi> 103.17. As it had no begining it knows no end whom he loves, he loves to the end outthorrow <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.1. <hi>I have loved thee with everlaſting loving kindneſs, Jerm,</hi> 31.3. and we would know wherein his Loye appeared eſpecially in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179273:4"/>his death which though it was a painful ſhamful curſed death, yet was he a volunteer in it, not forced to it, he had power to lay down his Life and power to take it up again. Yea he was earneſt to give a proof and vent his Love thus <hi>Luke</hi> 11.50. <hi>I have a Baptiſm to be Baptiſed with meaning of his dath,</hi> and O how! am <hi>I</hi> ſtraitned or pained till it be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and <hi>Pſ.</hi> 40. verſe 8. <hi>I delight to do thy will.</hi> as if he had ſaid. Father I will not debate nor prig anent the Ranſom of the Elect, I will come in your will for what you can charge on them: I am willing to undergo, We are ready to prig with him; ſo much we would do, but no more, ſo far we would go in his way, and no further, if he had ſtood ſo in our matters, we had periſhed eternally. 6ly. We ſhould know the purchaſe of his Death. 1. Juſtification, He has procured a Righteouſneſs to cover us, and that is our peace <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. We have no covering of our own, but that which is too narrow to wrap us in, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.20. If we ſhould walk in the light of our own Fire, and the ſparks of our own kindling, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.11. We ſhould lye down in ſorrow. 2dly. He has procured the Noble priviledge of Adoption to all that embrace him, <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.12: which ſecures Gods Peace, Pardon and Love. 3dly. Sanctification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. which is the Image of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. 4ly. Salvation is the purchaſe of the Blood of God ſhed as man, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28, doth not the heart affecting knowledge of all theſe tend to our peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Head.</hi> We muſt have the knowledge of the Spirit of Jeſus, there is a neceſſity for it <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. If any man have not the Spirit of Chiſt, he is none of his. We muſt know him in his Influences. 1. His inlighting influences revealing to us the deep things of God making us know the things freely given us of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 12. 2dly. In his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting influences, he bears this Style, the Comforter, the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.26. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.19. In the multitude of my thoughts within me thy comforts ſhall delight my Soul. Then in his Mortifying influences whereby he mortifies the Deeds of the Body, That our Souls may live, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. how deſirable is this to theſe wreſtling with the power of Luſt. Then in his aſſiſting influences, to the Exerciſe of all Graces and Duties, He is called the Spirit of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. The Spirit of Holineſs and Obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1, 4.5. The Spirit of Prayer and Mourning, <hi>Zecha.</hi> 12.10. The Spirit of wiſdom and underſtanding, Council and might, the Spirit of knowledge, and of the fear of the Lord, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11, 2: He makes Ordinances Lively, without whoſe ſhining, they ſignifie no more, than a Dyal where the Sun ſhines not, it is he who by his power decides controverſies as that. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18, 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ſhould crave and cherriſh this Spirit, who is freely given to the poor, as well as to the Rich, who ſeek him in earneſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11, 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Head,</hi> We ſhould know the Covenant of Grace in the Bleſſed terms of it, 1ſt. To know it in its freeneſs, God was not hired to make it, no Money, nor price required, only Hunger and Thirſt <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55, 1. Secondly, in the fulneſs of it, all that the poor Sinner needs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3. All Spiritual Bleſſings in Heavenly places in Chriſt, all things pertaining to Life and Godlineſs, 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.3. And what can be more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Thirdly, The Sureneſs of it, the heart affecting knowledge of it tends to peace; Firſt, No one promiſe ſhall fail, becauſe He is Faithfull, he will not break his Covenant, nor alter the thing that's gone out of his Lips, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 89, 33, 34. <hi>Joſua</hi> 21, 45. Appeals to the People that there failed not ought of any good thing which the Lord had ſpoken unto the Houſe of Iſrael; all came to paſs it is a well ordered Covenant, and is a Cordial at Death, <hi>David</hi> among his laſt words had this, 2 <hi>Samuel</hi> 23, 5. <q rend="inline">He hath made with me an Everlaſting Covenant, well ordered in all things, and ſure, and this is all my Salvation, and all my deſire.</q> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is ſure, the Stock is in a good hand, <hi>Jeſus</hi>'s Hand, the ſurity of the better Teſtament, we would ſoon have played the Bankrupt, but Chriſt makes all good. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. all the promiſes are in him yea and <hi>Amen. Thirdly.</hi> This Covenant ſmells the more of Grace, in that Chriſt engages to help us; to do our part, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <q rend="inline">He puts His
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179273:5"/>Laws in the minds of his People, and Writs them in their Hearts. <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> 26.27 The Lord Saith I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my ſtat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utes, and ye ſhall keep my Judgements and do them,</q> Fourtly, conſider the influence that the knowledge of this Covenant ſhould have upon our Heart and Life, not to make us looſe and wanton, but having theſe precious promiſes we ſhould cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. and 7.1. as you tender your Peace get this bargain made, This is the firſt and beſt way to peace, ſome ſpend their time tampering about duties, not puting a cloſe to this on every new emergency of trouble, They are in hazard to raze the Foundation: It would be a ſtrong Pillar of peace to have that to ſay I know my Covenanted God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and hates putting away. That is a brave word <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.5. One ſhall ſay I am the Lords, another ſhall call himſelf by the name of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and another ſhall Subſcrib with his Hand unto the Lord, and ſurname himſelf by the name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I know not if ye have taken time and laſure, to conſider and put this great matter to a point, upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on your own ſinfull ſelf deſtroyed caſe, and the offer of Chriſt in Goſpel terms to ſay it from your heart and ſubſcrib it with your hand, that you are and will be the Lords and his Chriſts, a back look of this I know has been a Cordial in a dying hour, when they have thought upon the time, place, and manner of their Covenanting with God, I wiſh you would all without delay lay, this matter to Heart.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Head.</hi> We ſhould know the rule of the Commands, <hi>Gal:</hi> 6.16. As many as walk according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercy and upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, firſt, we ſhould know the Commands and extent of them firſt as to the object, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are exceeding broad, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.96, they reach to all ſtations, relations and conditions Secondly as to the ſubject they reach the whole Man, Soul and Body, we muſt obey from the Heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. Thirdly we muſt know we daily breake the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. in many things we offend all and every breach deſerves death <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Rom</hi> 6.23. this tends to peace, chaſſing the Sinner into a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, the Prince of Peace who is the end of the Law for Rightouſneſs <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. Fourtly as you regaird your peace, allow not your ſelf in the breach of any Command, ſay not it is but this, it is but that, if it be a Sin, it's that which may coſt your Life, and and may go betwixt you and your part of Heaven, <hi>Pſalms</hi> 66.18. if I regaird iniquity in my heart ſayes he the Lord will not hear my Prayer, and ſayeth Chriſt <hi>Math.</hi> 5.19. whoſoever breaks one of theſe leaſt Commandments, and ſhall teach Men ſo, he ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven, we ſhowld have equal reſpect to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119, 6, 6. 128, Fifthly, we ſhould know the Command is in the promiſe, there are many ſevere Commands and as many ſweet promiſes, O how much tends this to peace; ſayeth the poor Sinner he hath Commanded us to love him, and he has promiſed to Circumciſe my Heart to love him <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. he has Commanded me to fear him, and he has promiſed to put his fear in my heart; That I may not depart from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. he has Commanded me to repent mourn and obey, and Pray, and he has prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſed his Spirit to all theſe effects <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26.27. <hi>Zechariah</hi> 12.10. he has Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to beleive, and he is the auther and finiſher of that Grace: So we muſt look from the Command to the promiſe and turn the promiſe to a Prayer, God will turn it to a performance, who works in hit People both to will and to do of his good pleaſure <hi>Philip</hi> 2, 13. let us ſay Lord give what thou Commands, and Command what thou wilt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Head. We muſt know Graces, and duties Graces I call them as they come from God, duties as exerciſed by us, and in the exerciſe of them, firſt we would be fervent cordial and affectionate, the heart is the fat of the Sacrifice, without which the Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179273:5"/>abhorrs it, <hi>Rom:</hi> 12.11. Be fervent in Spirit ſerving the Lord, And <hi>David</hi> ſayeth. <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 25.1. Unto thee O Lord do I lift up my Soul, and <hi>Hanna</hi> 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 1 15. Was a Woman of a ſorrowful Spirit, pouering out her Soul unto the Lord. 2dly. We ſhould be frequent in performance of Duties. <hi>Pſalms</hi> 62 8. Truſt in him at all times. <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 28 14. Happy is the Man that feareth always. 1 <hi>Theſs:</hi> 1.15. Pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing, which imports 1st We ſhould have ſet Meals for prayer, <hi>David</hi> had three times a day for ordiuar, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 55 17. Evening and Morning and at noon time of Day will I pray and call aloud, <hi>Danul.</hi> 7.10. Thrice a day was his uſe and Wont. <hi>David</hi> had his extraordinaries ſeven times a day. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.164. 2dly. It imports we ſhould have our hearts ay in frame, ready to pray on all occaſions. 3dly. That we ſhould by frequent in Ejaculations, which would hinder no Buſſineſs. 3dly. We ſhould be denyed to Duties when done, when we have done all things which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: We ſhould ſay we are unprofitable Servants, and have done but our Duty <hi>Luke</hi> 1710 a ſpice of conceit ſpoils the Beſt Dutys, as the dead flee doth the precious ointment, <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 10 1, <hi>Paul</hi> who abounded more in labours than others laid no ſtrels on them. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3 7 8. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1510 There is no peace to be expected otherways. 4tly. We muſt know that it is not Conſcience, but the Word of God, that is the Rule of Duty. <hi>Iſiah</hi> 8.10. To the Law and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe they have nothing of light in them, 'tis not what you think muſt order you that you have an Impulſe of mind <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> miſtook themſelves in this when they would have called for Fire from Heaven to conſume the miſcourtious <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritants,</hi> it was not a good Spirit that did bear in that motion upon them <hi>Luke</hi> 9 52, &amp;c Therefore Chriſt rebuked them.</p>
            <p>There are theſe particular duties you would exerciſe as you would have peace. Firſt you muſt be mourners and penitent as ſure as I ſpeak none will get peace but who lay the foundation in ſorrow, <hi>Iſai</hi> 61.2. he Comforts all that mourn <hi>Math.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Bleſsed are they that mourn for they ſhall be comforted.</hi> Secondly you would be in the exerciſe of Faith which workes by love <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>peace and Joy comes by beleiving Habbac.</hi> 2.4. <hi>The Juſt ſhall live by Faith. Iſai.</hi> 26.3. The Lord will keep his mind in perfect peace whoſe heart is ſtayed on him, becauſe he truſts in him. Thirdly, we ſhould be in the excrciſe of Love to God, and Love to our Neighbour which is the Sum of both Tables, <hi>He that loveth not knoweth not God, For God is love</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8. We ſhould love all perſons and things that belong to God, We ſhould love all men, with the Love of Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the Saints with the Love of Delight. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 16.2. Had we this love to God, and for His Sake love to one another: It would clear our Claim to two great Promiſes, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.28. <hi>All things work together for Good to all that love God,</hi> even the Croſs payes a Cuſtom of Advantage to them, and Chriſts ſays, <hi>John</hi> 14.21.23. <hi>He that loveth me ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest my ſelf to him, and we will come, and make our abode with him.</hi> 4tly. We ſhould exetciſe our ſelves to Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.7.8. This would clear our Title to the Promiſes of this Life. and of that which is to come. Which would yeild much peace. 5tly. We ſhould be in the Exerciſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Mindedneſs, and have our Converſation in Heaven. <hi>Philip:</hi> 3, 20. And our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffections above, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. The greateſt Serenity is in the higheſt Regions, Clouds and Storms are below. 6tly. We ſhould be in the Exerciſe of a well grounded hope, which would make us rejoyce in Tribulation. <hi>Rom:</hi> 2, 3. This is the Anchor of the Soul, that keeps the Veſſel calm in a Storm. <hi>Heb:</hi> 6 19. The Helmet or Head-piece, that wairds off the Stroaks of Satans ſmarting Temptations, <hi>Ephes:</hi> 6 17. 7tly. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces much to our peace to have the ſenſe of our Spiritual Poverty. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 9 18. The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179273:6"/>needy ſhall not always be forgotten, nor the Expectation of the Poor periſh for ever. And <hi>David</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 40 17. I am poor and needy but the Lord thinks on me, <hi>Math:</hi> 5 3. Blcſſed are the poor in Spirit. Theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven, The word is, Beggars in Spirit who are put oft to the throne of Grace for an Alms, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1823 The poor uſe Intreaties. <hi>Heb:</hi> 4 16. Through Chriſt we have Acceſs with boldneſs. to the throne of Grace, that we may ſind Mercy, and obtain Grace, <hi>Philip:</hi> 4, 6.7 Who make their Requeſt known to God, get the peace of God which paſſeth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Underſtanding to guard their Heart and Mind, and <hi>Hanna</hi> 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 1, 15, 18 Who pouered out her Soul to the Lord, went away and her Countenance was no more ſad. 8tly. We would ſtudy Sincerity in the performance of all Dutys, which makes much for peace, both in the greateſt Extremity of our Life, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1, 9, 12. When they had the Sentence of Death againſt them, this was their rejoyceing, the Teſtimony of their Conſcience, That in Simplicity and Godly Sincerity, not with fleſhly Wiſdom they had their Converſation in the World, and it yeilds peace in the laft Extremity of Death: <hi>Ezekiah</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Iſiah</hi> 38, 3. Lord Remember how <hi>I</hi> have walked before thee in Truth, and with a perfect heart.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Head.</hi> We ſhould know and conſider ſome things, in Reference to Croſſes, and Afflictions, as we would conſult our Peace. 1st. That they are covenanted Mercies, and no token of Fead, but conſiſtent with God's Loving Kindneſs, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 89, 30, to the 34. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119, 75. I know O Lord that in Faithfulneſs thou haſt afflicted me, that quiets the heart; The Saints bear not the Croſs alone, Chriſt takes the heavy lift that makes the Yoke eaſie, <hi>Iſiah</hi> 63, 9. In all our Afflictions He is afflicted, and is ſtill a Simpathſer. 2dly. The Saints have had their beſt days; under the Croſs, as <hi>John</hi> when baniſhed to the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Patmoſs, Revel:</hi> 1.10. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were made to ſing in the Stocks, <hi>Acts</hi> 16 24. The Lord cohſes ſome in the Furnace of Affliction, <hi>Iſiiah</hi> 48 10. There was a Godly Miniſter in this Nation, I heard him ſay upon Death-Bed his Suffering times were ſweeter to him, than his moſt ſolemn Communion Days. 4tly A well improven Croſs, is a piece of a Saints happineſs, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 94.12. Bleſſed is the Man whom the Lord chaftiſeth, and teacheth out of his Law, 5tly The Croſs is needful to prevent Sin <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2: 6. To purge out and take away Sin, <hi>Iſia</hi> 27 9. To make us more like God in holyneſs, <hi>Heb:</hi> 12 10. To give us Errands to the Throne of Grace, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50, 15. And to make us walk in fear, and be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to diſcover the Truth and Strength of Grace to ſtir up Grace to Exerciſe, in order to the produceing of the peaceable fruits of Righteouſneſs. <hi>Heb:</hi> 12 11. The Lords deſign is to diſtinguiſh betwixt the Wilderneſs and <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that we may Glorify His rich and free Grace, upholding and delivering us, and to make us Inſtrumental to Comfort others. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 4. And to draw our heart Heavenwards, to know theſe things tend to peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 8. We ſhould know the way how the Lord brings in poor Sinners, to Chriſt. firſt he kills, and then makes alive, wounds and then heals, <hi>Deuter:</hi> 32, 39, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 2 6. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6, 1. He convinces of the loſt undone Self-deſtroyed Caſe, by nature and courſe; a law work in ſome degrees paſſes on the Soul. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3 24. The Law is a School-Maſter to lead to Chriſt, thus the Sinner is made to enquire after a Deliverer, <hi>Rom:</hi> 7 24 Who ſhall deliver me ſays <hi>Paul.</hi> 2dly. A new light is broken up, that diſcovers Sin in its black Colours, ſmelling rank of Hell and a Beautie in Holyneſs and diſcovers the Neceſſity, Excellency, Willingneſs and Ability of Chriſt to ſave to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all that come to God in him, <hi>Heb:</hi> 7 25. He is ſeen to be the Chief of ten Thouſands, and altogether lovely. <hi>Cantic:</hi> 5 10 16, Him hath God the Father
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179273:6"/>ſealed <hi>John</hi> 6 27. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, he was ſent upon this Errand to open peoples eyes and turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they might receive the forgiveneſs of Sins, and Inheritance among them, which are ſanctified by Faith. that is in Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 26 18. Thus Sinners are called from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his marvelous light. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 29. 3dly. Then the heart is prepared by the Arm of <hi>Jebovah</hi> to receive the Impreſſions of Mercy in a through Renovation, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heart is removed, a plyable melting frame is given. <hi>Hezek</hi> 26, 26. 4tly The Soul is brought over to give Conſent to the Bargain, and to take Chriſt on Goſpel Terms, and ſay, <hi>Cantic:</hi> 2 16. My beloved is mine and I am his: In all which the exceeding greatneſs of his power cyths, workinging in them that beleive. <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 1 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 9. If you would have peace, you muſt have a practical knowledge of the wayes theſe ought to walk in that come home to Chriſt, I fear many miſtake it <hi>firſt</hi> in the difioulty of it, ſome think nothing but they may go eaſily to Heaven, and yet plump in to the Pit, lying down with a lie in their right Hand, <hi>Iſas</hi> 44.20. The Apoſtle ſayes the Righteous are ſcarcely faved, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18, and Chriſt ſayes the way is ſtrait <hi>Mathew.</hi> 7.14. therefore we ſhould ſuive to enter in at the ſttrait Gate; for many will ſeek to enter in, that ſhall not be able. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. <hi>Secondly</hi> this way is miſtaken in the Singularity of of it: It's not the common Road and Broad-Way, the whole World lyeth in Wickedneſs. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5 19. Be not conform to the World ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom</hi> 12, 2. Follow not the multitude to do evil ſays <hi>Moſes, Exod:</hi> 23 2. And Chriſt ſayeth except your Righteouſneſs exceed the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phareſees</hi> you cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>Math.</hi> 20. The <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſees</hi> ſaid <hi>John</hi> 7 48. Have any of the Rulers of the <hi>Phareſees</hi> beleived on him, and the Apoſtle ſays. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 26, Not many wiſe Men after the fleſh, not many Mighty, not many Noble are ſaved, Bleſſed be God it is not ſaid not any, but not many: Becauſe Chriſt has but few Friends and Followers among that Sort of People.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Head</hi> Who conſult their peace, would have a heart affecting knowledge of ſome things in reference to Death and Judgement. 1st. The certainty of it, it's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for all Men rich and poor noble and ignoble once, and but once to die, <hi>Heb</hi> 9 27 and after this to Judgement. There is no Diſcharge in that War. <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 8 8. 2dly To know the uncertainty of it as to time, place and manner, that we may may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Watch-Tower. <hi>Math:</hi> 24, 42, 43. 3dly It is our great Concern, to be prepared for Death and Judgement: It is a Worlds-Wonder, that many dye without ſtrange Terrours, not being prepared for Death, yet many graceleſs have no Bands in their Death. <hi>Pialms</hi> 73, 4. But ſad is their awakening, they are like a Man thurſt out at a ſlit of a high Tower in a dark night, we hear no din of the rich Gluttons Death, Luke 16 22 But the firſt news after is, that in Hell he lift up his eyes, and cryed O for a drop of cold water, to cool my tongue for I am tormented, in this Flame.</p>
            <p>Right Honourable and well Beloved, if peace of Conſcience be your Concernment, if to dye with Comfort be your Concernment, if everlaſting Well and Wo be your Concernment, if to be in Heaven, and to ſhun Hell be your Concernment, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Death and Judgment, is of greateſt and everlaſting Concernment. You have need to be ready and prepared, for Death will not wait one Moment for your readineſs; When that Meſſenger comes, there is no retaining of the Spirit. <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 8 8. It is vain then to wiſh, O for another hour! For another Day.</p>
            <p>I will tell you what is the beſt preparation for Death and Judgement, it's to live in Chriſt, and die in Chriſt <hi>Rom:</hi> 147. <hi>Gal:</hi> 2 20. 1ſt This is the way to get the ſting taken
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179273:7"/>out of Death, and Death ſwallowed up of Victory, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15 54 55. 2dly This is the way to be delivered from the fear of death. <hi>Heb:</hi> 2 14 15. 3ly This is the way to to be bleſt in your Death, <hi>Revel:</hi> 14 13. 4ly. This is the way to be made welcome to your Maſters joy with his Bleſſing. <hi>Mash:</hi> 25 23 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applications</hi> Right Honourable and well beloved, I earneſtly beceech you, as you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard peace wsth God, peace of your Souls, ſeriouſly to ponder in order to practiece, all the aforementioned Heads, as your greateſt Concernment: for the laft of death and Judgement, I muſt tell you who are called Gods, ye muſt die like Men <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 82.7. And all lye down alike in the duſt, and the Worms cover you <hi>Job</hi> 21. 26. your duſt will not be known from the Beggars. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5 10. you muſt all appear before the judgement Seat of Chriſt, the Word is <hi>be manefeſted,</hi> and lajd open be fore him who judges without reſpect of perſons. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17 and if you dye without ſound knoweldge and underſtanding tho' now you be in Honour you will be like and worſe than Beaſts that periſh <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 49, 20. We read of a King, <hi>Jerem:</hi> 22 18.19. Who died unlamented, and was buried with the Burial of an Aſs. You that now ſit on Benches, muſt ſtand at the Bar that Day: Satan has prevailed ſo far with many to put the Thoughts of Death far away, and to obliterate the Belief of Judgment, making them more Atheiſt than himſelf, <hi>James</hi> 2 9. The Devils believe and tremble. I remember near forty years agoe, when the Flood Gate of Prophanity was caſt wide open in <hi>Scotland</hi> [and no ſhutt to this Day] which paved the way to Prelacy, that gave too great Scouth to Prophane Inclinations: There was a profligate perſon of no mean quality, being admoniſhed by a noble Friend to mind Death and Judgement, for he behoved to reckon for his Debauchery, he ſaid if he thought on that he would go mad: But theſe who will not hear Admonition, now and Conſcience now will be tyed to endure his Reproof; who will tear them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when there is none to deliver. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50 21, 22. There will be a huge cry at that Day among theſe who hold their heads high now; Kings of the earth, great Men, Rich Men, Chief Captains, and mighty Men ſhall cry to the Mountains, and to the Rocks to fall on them, and hide them from the Face, of Him that ſits on the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb: For the Great Day of his Wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand. <hi>Revel:</hi> 2 15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your Character then will not cover you. Faithful Miniſters are deſpiſed by many, were we of a Soul betraying tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to deal with people according to their hearts deſire, to forbear right things, and ſpeak ſmooth things. <hi>Iſiah.</hi> 30, 10. And flatter them to their Ruine; They would embrace us, but becauſe we warn plainly having our Souls at the ſtake. <hi>Ezek</hi> 34 Being tender of Gods Glory, their Souls good and our own, they hate us in doing our Duty, and reproveing, which the Seripture expounds a kindneſs. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 141 5. And it imports a defect of the rational Faculty and brutiſh temper to hate reproof. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 12 1. What will ſuch ſay in the Day of Viſitation, when wrath ſeaſes on them. If ever God bring you to a ſenſe of your Condition, that word will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by you. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 28 23. He that rebukes a man ſhall find more favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fterwards, than he that flatters with the tongue: I doubt not there are in Hell this day, who are Curſing their Miniſters that flattered them in their Sins. I put two Queſtions to you, Firſt, how will you anſwer for this, that ye do that which ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn others, and Judge the Comitters thereof worthy of Death. And enact Laws againſt Sabbath-breaking, Swearing, Drunkeneſs and Uncleanneſs: you mock God, and are ſelf condemned; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. and 2. 21.22. Thou therefore which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf, thou that teacheſt a man not to Steal, doeſt thou
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179273:7"/>Steal, thou that ſayeſt a Man ſhould not commit Adultery; Doſt thou commit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery. Thou that abhorreſt Idols; doſt thou commit Saerilige: Secondly, how will any anſwer for this, that they Glory in what they cannot endure, the name of drunkard, would thou be called by that name, or the Swearer, or Whore-Monger; Would ye be content to have it Written upon your Tombs, or dwelings: here Lyes, or here dwells, the Drunkard, the Swearer, or Whore Munger. The Lord tells there is a Day coming when People ſhall know whoſe Word ſhall ſtand, his or theirs <hi>Jerem.</hi> 44.28.29. They ſhall know that his Word ſhall ſtand againſt them for evill, I do here in the name and and authority, of my Great Maſter Jeſus, whoſe Ambaſſador I am. Warn and Charge, all that hear me this Day, to compear before the Tribunal, and anſwer to their charge for unrepented of Drukenneſs, Uncleanneſs, Fornication, Adultery, Swearing Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Perjury, Covenant-Breaking, Teſting or being <hi>Gallios</hi> unconcerned in Gods Matters and your Souls; Sabbath-Breakers, Prayerleſs and you who have had any hand in the Late Perſecution of Gods Servants and People, make you ready make haſt, and ſtrive to get accompts cleared by Chriſt's Cautionry, I cannot ſet a Day, but it may be a few Hours, ſiſt ſome of you before the Judge: Think on it, be not abuſed when you come to Die by Carnal Freinds, or your own deceitful Hearts: I have known ſome when they have come to die call for the Miniſters, they hated and perſecuted before, and cryed out of their Sins with tears. I have known others that neither they nor their carnal Friends would ſuffer the Faithful to come near them, but the Montibank, who ſent them over the Border with the fig Leaf of a ſmooth abſolution: O betray not your own Souls, nor let others do it, thuart not your own Conſciences to pleaſe Men, as <hi>Pilate</hi> who found no fault in Chriſt, yet over the Belly of Warning ordered to ſcourge and crucifie him, to pleaſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the people. Right Honourable, There has not been a Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iament, but before a next ſome members have gone off the Stage, and ſome of the moſt Honourable for quality and beſt for piety are gone within theſe few Years. 'tis hard to know who goes next, make you ready, I muſt teſl you a wrong Step in Death can never be mended <hi>Eccles.</hi> 11.13 In the Place where the Tree falls there it lies; What ever changes may be in a Mans life, after Death there is none, but etern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al well or eternal wo.</p>
            <p>Now there be ſeveral things we ſhould know and conſider in reference to the peace of the Church and Land, and herein both Rulers and People ſhould Act their part.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we ſhould have our hearts, affected with reflection on the crying Sins of the Land, our iniquity like the Wind; has taken us away <hi>Jſai.</hi> 64.6. That of <hi>Hoſea</hi> may be applyed 4. Chap. 1.2. The Lord hath a controverſie with the Inhabitants of the Land, becauſe there is no Truth nor Mercy, nor Knowledge of God, in the Land, by Swearing and Lying, and Killing and Stealing, and commiting Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; they break out, and Blood, toucheth Blood: And People become impudent. As if they would give God a defiyance, they commit Abominations and are not aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, neither do they bluſh <hi>Jerem</hi> 8.12. They diſpiſe a ſaviour in Goſpel ordinances.</p>
            <p>Secondly we ſhould conſider, that there is a dark and thick Cloud of wrath and judgement, hanging over us, the Lord threatning as <hi>Liviticus</hi> 26.24. to heat the Furnace yet Seven times more, have we not had ſad Stroaks, decay of Trade, Dearth, Famine, Mortality of Man and Beaſt, and ſomething of Fire and Sword. I look upon all theſe as the begining of ſorrows if matters mend not amongſt us; Let us hearken to that word. <hi>Zephamach</hi> 2 1. 2. Gather your ſelves together, yea Gather together a Nation not deſired before the decree bring forth, before the day paſs as chaff, before the fierce anger of the Lord, come upon you &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:179273:8"/>
            <p n="1">1, Therefore I would, preſs, 1. That ye wreſtle with God by Prayer at the Throne of Grace <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 46.7. It's ſaid the Lord of Hoſts is with us, the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> is our refuge; whence got <hi>Jacob</hi> the new name <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he prevailed as a Prince by ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let us cry mightily to God, that he would rent the Heavens, and come down; And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Mountains flow down at his preſence. <hi>Iſai</hi> 64.1.7. That the Lord would come with healing to Souls and awaken the Conſciences of ſmall and great, that are faſt a ſleep in damnable ſecurity. For there are few that call on God, or ſtir up themſelves to take hold of him.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Know it is our part to ſtudy, mourning and amendment, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.40, 41. Let us ſearch and try our ways, and turn again unto the Lord: Let us lift up our heart with our hands, to God in the Heavens. <hi>Zechariah</hi> 12.13. Perſons a part, and Families a part mourning, that would be a Door of hope in the Valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and mourning, muſt begin at Perſons, come to Families, and ſpread through the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then might we ſay as <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.2. Now is there hope in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> concerning this thing.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. Study Zeal and courage for the way and work of God, never be aſhamed of it. Be Zealous and repent ſays Chriſt <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.19. Be of good courage, lay out your ſelves as you are called in your ſphere to contend forthe faith, <hi>inde</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4ly. Study unity and love, and beware of undue contendings unite in what is true and, good if ye bite and devoure one another ye may be conſumed one of another <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.5. The beginning of ſtrife is like the opening of Waters to overflow. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 17.14. Therefor leave off contention, before it be medled with, I confeſs there is a lawfull contending not only for truth, and the Faith of the Goſpel, but even for inferiour things. <hi>Job</hi> 31.13. &amp;c. having the Dread of God on his Heart, admits his hirelings to offer their Grievances and reaſon their cauſe, but the riſe of debates would be examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if from Pride and envy, then confuſion and every evil work, would be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.16 there be due, ſeaſonable and right methods and meaſures, that would be followed, a miſtake in theſe may mar a very cleanly deſign, and in ſtead of bringing Water to quench the Fire, may prove oyl to encreaſs the Flame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> his commendation will never die <hi>Genes.</hi> 13. who though he was Superior and Elder than <hi>Lot,</hi> yet to avoid unſeaſonable contendings when the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> were in the Land, yeilded to <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe choiſe proved his puniſhment: and if it be no diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the higheſt to condeſcend to theſe below them, even ſuppoſeing a tranſgreſſion it is their Glory to paſs it over <hi>Proverbs</hi> 19.11. far more is it the bound duty of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors to yeild and not unmannerly to prig with thoſe above them, where, yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be without manifeſt prejudice to Truth and Peace, There be two things ſuppoſed to have influence on deviſion and Faction, which is a work of the Devil, a work of the Fleſh, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.20. There is a Defect and an Exceſs. Firſt, a defect of ſingleneſs and ſincerity, If Men were al! ſingle-Hearted, ſincere, ſelf-denyed, and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publick-Spirited, they would meet unite, and cloſe without claſhing or noiſe. Secondly, there is exceſs the excreſſence and knottiſneſs of humor and intereſt that makes Men uneaſie and to daſh upon, and grate one another, but theſe who lay the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and ſow the Seeds of diviſion; or are abatters of it, either in Church or State, do the abominable thing which the Lord hates, <hi>Prov;</hi> 6, 16, 19, And cannot be long hid. <hi>Nemo poteſt diu ſuſtinere Perſonam fictam Prov.</hi> 26.26. He that covereth his hatred with deceits his wickedneſs ſhall be made known before the whole Congregation, ſuch marrs, Suites and Propoſals to them, and by them; being jealouſed of mixt intereſts and and deſigns, which the ſimpler ſort cannot underſtand and diſcern. 2. <hi>Samuel</hi> 15.11.</p>
            <p>Application, We may take up a Lamentation, and regrate there be few that know the way of peace, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59.8. They neither deſire nor apply themſelves to know theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179273:8"/>things. <hi>Heſea</hi> 8.12. I have Written to them ſayeth the Lord the great things of my Law, and they counted them as a ſtrange thing, how many live without God, and without Chriſt in the World, and have loſt the ſenſe of God, and pulſs of Conſcience, it were eaſie to prove the greateſt part to be Fools, and ignorant of theſe things that belong to peace. I ſhall give you ſour notes of a Fool, Firſt he that prefers Huſks to wholſom Food, as the Prodigal <hi>Luke</hi> 15. Secondly, he that wants ſenſes to diſcern; and makes choiſe of a broken Ciſtern, forſakeing the Fountain, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.12.13. 3ly. he that wants fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight to provide for time to come <hi>Math.</hi> 25. The fooliſh Virgins had emptie Lamps. 4ly he that puts a Knife to his own Throat <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.36. he that Sins againſt me ſayes Chriſt wrongs his own Soul, all they that hate me love Death, there be Four ſorts of Perſons that the Scripture proves, to be arrant Sots and Fools. 1ſt, the Perſecuter God calls him a Feol who eats up his People, as they eat Bread <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 14.1.4. they know not God has diſcharged Perſecution, and is concerned in the wrongs done to his People <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 105.14.15. 2ly The Lord reſents what wrongs are done to his People, as done to himſelf <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4. <hi>Saul Saul</hi> why Perſecuteſt thou me, They peirce Chriſt through the ſides of his Freinds 4ly they are Fools becauſe they are Prayerleſs and Scriptureleſs, they call not upon the Lord <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 14.4, they caſt the Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind their back, and therefore they Perſecute, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.26. 5ly they come Foul off with it as the inſtances of <hi>Pharorh, Herod Haman. Darius,</hi> Courtiers. They proved all Fools in the end <hi>Exad.</hi> 14. <hi>Eſther.</hi> 8. <hi>Acts.</hi> 12. <hi>Dantel.</hi> 6. Secondly, the Proud Man he is a Fool, he gets the ſame name with the Fool, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. the word, in the Original, fignifies Smoak, which ſayes the Proud Man is puffed up with Stinking Air, Firſt, he conſiders not that God has prohibite Pride, and that Pride hinders many a good turn. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 13.15 and prompts to many an ill turn, the Curſed Proud are from Gods Commandments. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.21. and the wicked through the Pride of his countenance perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes the Poor and will not Seek God <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 102 4. Pride is the dead Flee in the A pothecarys Ointment, it ſpilt all the Pharaſies duties <hi>Luke</hi> 18. ſuch Perclaim War againſt the God of Heaven and makes him an Enemy 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. it has brought many low, and prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them Fools in the end <hi>Proverbs</hi> 16.18. Thirdly the Scripture makes the covetous Man a Fool, he knows not that covetouſneſs is a hainous tranſgreſſion in Gods account, no leſs than Idolatrie. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. ſuch Perſons are abhorred of the Lord. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 10.3 Their temper hinders profiting under means, their care choacks the Seed of the Word. <hi>Math.</hi> 13. They are in hazard of a ſad ſurpriſe <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. they hinder their own, thriveing, There is that withholdeth more than is meet, and it tendeth to poverty. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 11.24. He makes a Fools bargain, and loſſes-more than he gains, when he loſſes his Soul. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.18.</p>
            <p>The Voluptuous and Luxurious they are Fools, they are plagued and prove a Prognoſtick of the evil of the laſt times. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3 4. They are dead while they live 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5 6. There pleaſures are ſhort lived like the crackling of Thorns under the Pot. <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 7 6. <hi>Heb:</hi> 11 25. There is a ſong to follow that will eat out all the Rememberance of their former Joy. <hi>Iſiah.</hi> 47 8. <hi>&amp;c. Revel:</hi> 18 7 8 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their way brings both poverty and pain, which they dream not of. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 21 17 23 29.. Aud they ſhall mourn at the laſt, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 5 11. When they feel what they feared not, is it not for a Lamentation that the greateſt part befool themſelves? 1ſt, how many groſly ignorant have their hopes to be ſaved: Yet <hi>Iſiah</hi> 27 11. The Lord ſays he has no favour for them, 2 <hi>Theſs:</hi> 1 8. Chriſt at the Laſt Day will take, Vengance on them. 2dly. How many live in black Atheiſm and Prophanity. Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, Unclean and think to be ſaved, and yet the Lord ſays
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179273:9"/>becauſe of theſe things his Wrath comes (on the Children of Diſobedience, and ſuch ſhall be caſt in the Lake, <hi>Revel:</hi> 21 8. 3dly. Many never had a night Senſe of Sin and Loſtneſs, and yet hoped to be ſaved, whereas the right hope of Heaven never lodged in him, who never ſaw he was in hazard of Hell, <hi>John</hi> 16 9. Conviction is the firſt Step of turning to God. 4tly. Many are altogether taken up with the World unconcerned in Gods Glory or their own Salvation, and yet hope to be ſaved: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Lord ſays <hi>Philip</hi> 3 19, Their end is Deſtruction. 5ly. There are ſome have got many Warnings, and heard many Preachings and never were touched with any of them like theſe. <hi>Deuter:</hi> 29 19 20. When they hear the Words of the Curſe, they bleſs themſelves in their Hearts, ſaving they ſhall have Peace, although they walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fter the Imagination of their own heart, and add Drukenneſs to thirſt, But the Lord ſays He will not ſpare His Anger, and Jealouſie ſhall ſmoak againſt that Man, and all the Curſes that are written in this Book ſhall be upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his name under Heaven, ſhould not this his Alarm ſecure Souls; I will give you one Mark of them, they love the flattering cheat who claps their head in their Sins, and hates the Faithful ſearching Preacher, who is their beſt Friend.</p>
            <p>But how comes it that people befool themſelves and ſets not their Minds to know things that belong to Peace. 1ſt They are in the Viſible Church, and enjoy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Benefites of the People of God, ſuch may have Heavens door cloſed on them. <hi>Math:</hi> 7 22 23. Some that heard Chriſt propheſre in their Streets, he boaſts them to depart. 2ly they paint A God all mercy and conſider not that he is juſt and tender of his honour they Shape A God to their own mind, that is as well pleaſed with their way as they themſelves the Lord ſayeth <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.21. 2, theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence, thou thought that I was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf, but I will reprove thee, and ſet them in order, before thine Eyes. Now conſider this ye that forget God, leaſt I tear you in peices, while there is none to deliver. He will draw up in Battle array, the Sins of ſuch, and every Sin as it were dipt in the Vinegar of his Wrath, that ſhall peirce like a Dart through the Heart and the Liver. 3ly ſome dream all will be well with them. for they thrive in the World, they have health and wealth and credit. yet God may give thee thy Hearts deſire in theſe things and ſend Leanneſs to thy Soul, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 106. 15. 4ly ſome think if they Periſh they will have many marrows, It will be no eaſe to you to go to Hell in a throng. every one there will kindle anothers Fire, and make it the hoter, <hi>Math.</hi> 13 30. ſays Chriſt bind them in bundles and Burn them, pack them to together, the Unclean, the Drunkard's, the Drunkard will curſe his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever he ſaw their Faces, ſo will the Whore-Munger and Harlot.</p>
            <p>Would you have the tokens of theſe that know the things that belong to their peace, and are made wiſe by Chriſt. unto Salvation. Firſt, ſuch are overawed with apprehenſions of God, he is their Fear, and he is their dread, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.13 <hi>Pſaim.</hi> 111.10. <hi>Genes.</hi> 39.9. <hi>Joſeph</hi> was truely wiſe 2ly they who prize things according to their worth, and and make right choiſe as <hi>Paul. Philip</hi> 3.72 8, who counted all things lofs and dung for the excellencie of the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt his Lord; and <hi>David Pſalm.</hi> 4.6.7. who preferred the lifting up of the Lord's countenance on him to any other good. 3ly ſuch will not prig with Chriſt, but will Sell all for the Field, where the Pearle is <hi>Mat.</hi> 13 44. 4ly ſuch will mannage time well, that is a note of a ſound underſtanding to conſider the Latter end <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.29 ſo teach us to number our Dayes ſays <hi>Moſes Pſalm.</hi> 90.12. that we may apply our Hearts to wiſdom, <hi>Job</hi> was wiſe. 14.14 all the Dayes of my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time will I wait till my change come. I know not when I riſe at Morn if ever I ſee another Day, it is wiſdom to redeem time <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.15.16. we have no more
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179273:9"/>time we can call our own but the preſent time this Day, yeſterday is not ours it is gone and will not return, and we are not ſure of to Morrow <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 27.1. we ſhould the rather conſider time becauſe much work lyes undone, and ſlighting of time puts many to the Fools repentance out of time, they who know what belongs to their peace will ſtudy ſound obedience, and reduce knowledge to practice, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 111.10. A good underſtanding have all they that do his Commands <hi>John</hi> 13.17. If ye know theſe things ſayes Chriſt, happy are ye if ye do them, this is the beſt proof, a fruitful and ſhineing converſation.</p>
            <p>Now I would ſpeak to all, Eſpecially to Rulers and Judges, as you would evidence your Knowledge and Conſideration, of what belongs, either to your Souls Peace, or the Peace of the Church and Land, there are ſome things you would beware of, and ſome things you would have and do</p>
            <p n="1">1. Beware of Rigour Tyranny, and Oppreſſion, or Inyeighing with bitterneſs againſt People, where there is no cauſe, by inflicting puniſhment, either unjuſtly where there is no Fault, or immoderatly, unſeaſonably and baſely, where there is a Fault, There is an obligation on Rulers, thus to make Conſcience of Dutys to inferiors, he Rules with moſt Comfort and Confidence, who keeps moſt room in Peoples Affections; and weakens them not, and they are moſt likly to be the Men of the Promiſe, to Build the Old waſte places; to raiſe up the Foundation of many Generations, to be called the Repairers of Breaches, the Reſtorers of Paths to dwell in, who looſe the Bonds of Wickedneſs, undo heavy burdens, and let the Oppreſſed go free, and break every Yoke, and eaſe People of juſt grievances, and impoſe not, nor continue, what is forbidden or condemnemned, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.6.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Be not too Credulous, Try before ye Truſt, a near Relation may whiſper, what is dang rous and proves a ſnare 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.3. <hi>Achaſiach</hi> his Mother councilled him to do wickedly. <hi>Saul</hi> hearkened to falſe deceitful Sclandarous <hi>Doeg Pſalm,</hi> 52. a great Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of <hi>David,</hi> who had taken great Ventures for him.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. Beware of Self-ſeeking <hi>Baruch, Jer.</hi> 3.45. a Good Man is reproved for ſeeking great things to himſelf, when the Lord threatned Deſolation, <hi>Pauls</hi> Complains <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.21. All ſeek their own things, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt, this made <hi>Judas</hi> betray Chriſt, and that with a Kiſs, and <hi>Pilate</hi> to Crucify Him, It is a mark of diſhonour and Brand of Infamy, Eſpecially in Great Men to be Self-Seekers, to live wholly to themſelves, like the Grave, wherein all that is gotten is buried, and nothing brought forth to publick benefite; It may be written on the Tombs of theſe, ſuch a Man ſought himſelf while he lived, and loſſed himſelf when he dyed: For this Self, dis ſpirits Men, making them cold and cowardly in Gods Cauſe, and becomes a Maſter, for the Lords Cauſe, ſhake off its Government, reſiſt its Reaſonings, diſobey its Commands, follow not its inclinations, to ſatisfy its Luſtings.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. Prefer not ſecular Affairs to the Lords, ſuch were reproved. <hi>Hagai</hi> 1. when the Lords Houſe lay waſte.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. Beware of Pride and upliftedneſs of Spirit; The Lord laid the Pride of <hi>Pharoch, Hamon, Herod,</hi> and the King of <hi>Aſſiria,</hi> True Wiſdom humbles and advances to Honour, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 15.33.</p>
            <p n="6">6ly. Overlook not perſons of a dangerous complexion by cruel Indulgence, one <hi>Achan,</hi> indangered the wholeCamp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſuch would be put out of Capacity to hazard Church or State, I am not of the cruel temper of that Man, who exhortd the Lords of Juſticiary at <hi>Jedburgh.</hi> To dye their Scarlet Robs in the Phanaticks Scarlet Blood.</p>
            <p>We hear of ſome intending to addreſs this Honourable Court, as if Men ſhould be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179273:10"/>exempted from Church Cenſure, who are Supinely negligent, Coutumacious, Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous or guilty of Immoralities, We hope, they will not find a ſhelter in this Honourable Aſſembly: They plead, that becauſe they have qualified themſelves, and has a Protection of His Majeſty that will exeem them: 'Tis true, ſome of them have qualified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in proceſs of time, at the end of Days, as <hi>Cain</hi> brought his offering, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3. After ſeveral Years out-ſtanding: One more ingenuous than others, Confeſſed, he never intended it, till he loſt hope of the return of a New Patron: How diſſaffected they are and how much they foſter the diſaffected, who are their moſt Bon-Companions, and continue the Schiſm is well known, and I fear they and ſome others are not that length in Loyalty, that <hi>Ephraim</hi> was in Religion, to be a Cake not turned warm in the one ſide, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7, 8. And that in this reſpect, many are a ſtep out of the Road to Heaven, If they have ſworn deceitfully, and not ſpoken truth in their hearts, (<hi>Pſalm.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 24.4.) If their heart and hand, and heart and tongue have not correſponded, they have taken Gods Name in vain, and ſuch are reckoned Gods Enemies, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.22. It is a griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, that the Intruſions of ſuch ſhould be tolerate, and then ſetting up Meeting-Houſes to marr Legal Eſtabliſhments, and eſpecially where there are Legal Eſtabliſhments: We hope this Honourable Court will Redreſs it, as ye would not appear to caſt down with one hand what ye Build with another.</p>
            <p>Poſitively as you would prove your underſtanding in theſe things that belong to your Peace 1ſt. You would have a good foreſight, and not be wilfull in what may be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, Princes and Magiſtrates in their Reſolutions and Purpoſes would have a Reſerve to change Meaſures on ſecond Thoughts, eſpecially in ſecular Concerns; So did <hi>David</hi> when provocked by an unmannerly Clown, <hi>Nabal</hi> 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 25. But in things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Glory, Conſtancy is a Commendation, <hi>David</hi> never changed his purpoſe to pay his Vows, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66 13 14. And to build the Houſe of God, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 132 4</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Study a right ordering of the State in Civil Affairs, for it will never be well with the Church, if not well with the State, The wicked walk on every ſide when vileſt Men are exalted, <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 12 8. When the Righteous are in Authority the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, but when the wicked bear rule the people mourn. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 29 2.</p>
            <p>There be four Sorts of perſons dangerous to Crowned-Heads to run them on precipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 1ſl. Sycophants and Flatterers as <hi>Achabs</hi> falſe Prophets, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 2ly, The Envious as <hi>Dariuſ's</hi> Courtiers <hi>Daniel</hi> 6 3dly The ſelfiſh, ambitious, and covetous as <hi>Haman.</hi> 4ly Heady and young Councellours like <hi>Rehoboam</hi> who occaſioned the Revolt, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. It is peoples part to pray that Kings make a choice of Favorites as <hi>Exodus</hi> 18 21. 1st Able Men for Greatneſs, Courage, Reſolution and Conſtancy of Mind. 2dly Men fearing God. 3dly Faithful Men that love the Truth. 4tly Men hating Covetouſneſs and Bribes, which blows duſt in the eyes of the Wiſe</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. It ſpeaks underſtanding in Magiſtrates their care that Juſtice be diſpenced diſcreetly, ſpeedily, expeding Cauſes [not fretting Spirits by undue delays) Impartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity univerſally to all, reſolutly, couragiouſly, righteouſly, exactly ſoberly and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, thus Judgement ſhall return to Righteouſneſs, and all the Upright in heart ſhall follow it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94 15. Good Laws which are the Sinniews of Societies would be enacted the greateſt perfection whereof ſtands. 1st. In their conformity to the prime and Eternal Law of God. 2dly. In their vigorous Execution, the failing whereof is a great Grievance, written Laws are for direction, and the Living Law (which is the Magiſtrate) is for action to ſee theſe Laws obeyed, and in your Laws it were very meet there were a proviſion, with reſpect to the Sufferers of the late times, Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the moſt eminent of them, who have ſuffered in their perſons and poſterity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be a redreſs of Wrongs and injuries they have endured.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:179273:10"/>
            <p>But Rulers would bend their Underſtanding and Conſideration chiefly in their care about Religious Concerns, to promote Piety and Zions Wellfare. <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 132 and 137 1ſt. By their Commands. <hi>Aſa</hi> commanded <hi>Judah</hi> to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers. and do his Law and Commandments, 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 14 24. 2dly By the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their Perſons and Familys as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Joſhua.</hi> 3dly By encourageing and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a pious and faithful Miniſtry, men according to Gods heart, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 15 4ly. To promote the true Worſhip of God and aboliſh falſe Worſhip, Superſtition, and all Monuments of Idolatry, there are ſome in <hi>Scotland</hi> preſume upon an intollerable Innovation to make uſe of the Service-Book which hath no edge, I have heard ſome of the hearers of it ſay it would be long before the hearing of it would make a ſore heart for Sin, This Church could never endure it, nor durſt Prelates in their greateſt hight Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon it: It is known how much of it is copied out of the Popiſh Breviary; I will not comment upon the Verdict of a great perſon who called that Service an ill ſaid Maſs, for the ridiculous Abſurdities and Falſities of it 1ſt They may be ſeen at large in <hi>Baxters</hi> Life. 5tly. There would be a ſpeciall Care to viſite, and ſettle Seminaries of Learning with pious and learned men. It is an old Trick of <hi>Rome</hi> to poyſon theſe Fountains. 6tly. Magiſtrates would have a ſpecial care to preſerve the true Government in Chriſts Church by Presbetry, which differs as much from Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as a ſtone Wall doth from a Mud-Wall; We own this Government to be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right, and for the Churches intrinſick Power and Priviledges we hold them of no ſecular power, but of Jeſus Chriſt the head of the Church, and owned as ſuch in our Confeſſion of Faith, which is ratified in Parliament; This Government and the Power thereof depends not upon the Suffrages of Men which are alterable, no Mans Will being a Standard in this Matter; It would import Chriſt an imperfect King, if he had left it to Mens Arbitriment to come and go upon, <hi>Moſes</hi> might not alter a pin from the Patern ſhewed in the Mount, <hi>Exod</hi> 25 9. And if <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful in the Houſe of God as a Servant, much more Chriſt as a Son, whoſe Houſe we are, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. Chriſt will not deny <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due; nor will he want his own, nor be pleaſed with the pair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Priveledges of his Church, for the Liberty and Exerciſe of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we have reaſon to bleſs the Lord for the Countenance and Encouragement we have from our Gracious, Chriſtian, and Proteſtant King and we are hopeful he will not impair but inlarge the ſame. It is true the Church exerciſed their power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of God ſome hundreds of years before there was a Chriſtian Magiſtrate to own her, which power as far as we could reach we uſed in times of Perſecution, and Church-Officers muſt uſe, when Magiſtrates are Enemies, but bleſſed be God we are not under that Temptation. I have before other Seſſions of Parliament proven our Government in all reſpects founded on the Word of God, and moſt anſwerable to the Ends of an eſtabliſhed Miniſtry. To hold out the wild Boar that would corrupt both Doctrine and Manners, and guard beſt againſt Vice and Error, and keep Ordinances beſt from pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and the Church from Infection, and we may venture the Tryal as the Prophet did. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. When the people halted between two Opinions, doubting whether God was God or <hi>Baal</hi> was God, the Prophet ventured the Matter upon this that God that anſwers by fire let him be God, and he carryed it, that it was acknowledged the Lord He was God, that did bear Witneſs by fire from Hheven, and <hi>Baal</hi> was found to be but a dead and a deaf God that could not anſwer the Expectation of his Worſhipers. Now if the Government which we own be not moſt witneſſed to from Heaven by the Spirit in his Operations of Conviction, Converſion and Conſolation of Souls: Let God and the World judge: Had we not been perſwaded of theſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179273:11"/>things, what fools had we been to have ſuffered one year, let be ſo many Years ſeverity on that Account. I judge few in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſober judicious and Inegnuous will ſpond their breath againſt this Intereſt and if any, it is moſtly theſe who indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and love to be indulged in their Luſts, and loves Elbow-Room to Sin without Control.</p>
            <p>Right Honourable and well-beloved ye would be wiſe to your ſelves to befriend the Church in all her Concerns, for the Arks ſake, God bleſſed <hi>Obededom</hi> in his perſon, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Friends. 1 <hi>Cron:</hi> 13, You would be careful the Churches Revenues be neither embazled miſimproven or miſſaplyed.</p>
            <p>That Rulers of all Ranks ſhould endeavour knowledge and underſtanding to diſcern Good and evil, rightly to time and circumſtantiat Actions is clear <hi>Deut</hi> 1 13. <hi>Eccles:</hi> 8 5. And it is threatned as a Judgment when Princes are Babes in Underſtanding <hi>Iſiah</hi> 3 4 5 <hi>David</hi> prays for Underſtanding to <hi>Solomon</hi> 1 <hi>Cronities</hi> 29 19. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>Solomon</hi> for himſelf. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3 9. There be Three Reaſons why Magiſtrates ſhould labour to have Underſtanding, 1st, The figure they bear by their Office imported in their Styles, being called Gods, Saviours, Fathers. Eyes, Pillars, heads of the Body and Overſeers. 2dly. God ſeverly threatens Magiſtrates that misbehave, as being neither above Inſtruction nor Correction if they fail. <hi>Job</hi> 12 21. He poures Contempt upon Princes and weakens the Strength of the Mighty. <hi>Pſal</hi> 110 5. He ſtrikes through Kings in the day of his wrath <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76 12. He is terrible to the Kings of the Earth, he ſhall cut off the Spirits of Princes.</p>
            <p>3dly Becauſe they are lyable to many Difficultys and Dangers, great is their Task, to know the State of the People, to repreſs the Inſolencies of the proud, to miniſter Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to all.</p>
            <p>I would warn both Magiſtrates and people to know and watch againſt theſe evilly which threatens both Church and State with Judgements, as namely, 1ſt When Men loath not their own hearts for unprofitableneſs under Ordinances, but weary of them</p>
            <p>2dly. When Men profeſſing the fear of the ſame God, are mutually contentious. 3ly Breaking of Vows to the Lord, not cleaving to his Ordinances. 4ly. Peoples going to Ordinances, and not going to the God of Ordinances for the Bleſſing. 5tly. When Chriſt is not received in Ordinances, nor the Motions of his Spirit cheriſhed. 6tly When people are groſſly prophane in Talk and walk, and come to that hight of Sin as to caſt off all reproof, all Dread and Aw of God. 7tly Peoples frequent, familiar, and needleſs haunting with perſons perverſe, in Principles and Practices, whereby they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of their Sins, receive of their Plagues, and get a Snare to their Soul, <hi>Revel.</hi> 84. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 22 24.25. This has been the neck-break of this Generation eſpecially to the younger ſort. Companions of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 3 20. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayeth <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10 8. He that breaks an hedge, a Serpent ſhall bite him, there is a hedge of a ſix fold Prohibition. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 4 14 15. Enter not into the path of the Wicked and go not in the way of evil Men, avoid it, paſs not by it, turn from it, and paſs away: They who leap over this hedge may lay their account to ſmart for it.</p>
            <p>I would add a few things people ſhould know as their Bound Duty to Magiſtrates 1st. To pay them all due Reſpect and Honour. 2dly. All due obedience in the Lord. 3dly Fidelity to their perſons and Authority. 4tly Aid and Help. and that 1ſt. By Faithful Counſel and Advice when called, and the Diſcovery of ſecret Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Plots. 2ly By rich Rebates, without a grudge paying Cuſtom and Tribute, and giving all needful Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap> for the Safety of the King, the Security of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſafety of the Common Wealth, which was long ſince reckoned a Law above all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179273:11"/>Laws. 3dly. We ſhould give Aid by our perſons both againſt Country Rebels and forraign Enemies, venturing our Lives for them both in Peace and War. 2. <hi>Samnel</hi> 21 16: and 23 6. 4tly. By our prayers. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2 2. That we may live under their Government a peaceable and quiet Life in all Godlyneſs and honeſty, for Magiſtrates neither ſtand nor fall to themſelves, eſpecially So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns, becauſe they are the Pillars of the Kingdom. Let me ſmite King <hi>Saul</hi> but this once ſaid <hi>Abiſhas</hi> and the Kingdom ſhall be thine, and the Victory thine 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 26.8. ſo ſaid <hi>Achitopbel,</hi> let me Smite King <hi>David</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the and 2, <hi>Samuel</hi> 17.2.3. When <hi>Alexander</hi> Died the Army was but on Man leſs, but it was compared by the wiſe, to the Cyclops, which had its only Eye Bored out, the Supream Magiſtrate carrys about, not only his own Life, but the Life of Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands depends on his ſafety, 2. <hi>Samuel</hi> 18.3 2. <hi>Samuel</hi> 21.17. Thou ſhalt not go forth any more with us to battle, ſaid the People leaſt thou quench the light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for thy life is worth a Thouſand of ours.</p>
            <p>Shall not our Hearts be enlarged in bleſſing of God, for our Gracious King; whom he ſent to be a deliverer, to ſave theſe Lands from Popery and Slavery, and us alſo from Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie a yoke which neither we nor our Fathers were able to bear, and ſhall not our Souls be lifted up in ſervant ſupplicatious to God for him, in whoſe Safety the ſafety of the three Kingdoms is ſo much bound up, who ventured his all for us, when we were upon the brink of Periſhing, It is good our part to beg of God, to give him a large and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heart, and to multiply bleſſings of all ſorts upon him, bleſſings both of the right and left Hand, to give him length of Days. and make him a laſting bleſſing, to thoſe Nations, to give hin both the upper and neather Springs, and that his Crown may floriſh on his head, and all his Enemies Cloathed with ſhame, we are concerned to Pray for the King, and Magiſtrats of all ranks. that they may be truely religious, becauſe of the power oſ their example to good or evil, their vices paſs current for vertues, and ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a faſhon, be their Commands never ſo great, they Command moſt by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exhort.</hi> My laſt Exhortation to you all Right Honourable and well Beloved, is that ye acquaint your Selves with the Word of God, which makes the ſimple wiſe, many of you are too great Strangers to it, ſome are branded <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10.6. the Word of the Lord is to them a reproach, they have no delight in it, they mock Piety and the Scriptures the rule of piety ſuch are in the higheſt Claſs of Sinners in the Seat of the ſcornful <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1.1. Which is rendered by the Septuagint the ſeat of Peſtilence, ſuch are plagued in their Spirits, and are the Plague of their Generation, and alas! too rife amongſt us, God will make their Bonds ſtrong <hi>Ilas</hi> 28 22. he will caſt a chain of his wrath about them, which if mercy and repentance prevent not, will grip, and ſmart them to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>You would obſerve the Word in all the parts of it, 1. In the promiſes to believe them, to encourage you to Piety and Virtue, ſuch as theſe, <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 84 11. The Lord God is a Sun and Shield, he will give Grace and Glory, and withhold no good thing from them that walk uprightly, <hi>Jerem:</hi> 32 40. This is the Covenant that I will make with you, I will never depart from you to do you good, and I will put my fear in your hearts that you ſhall not depart from me. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8 28. All things ſhall Work together for good to them that love God, and are the called according to his, Purpoſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23. whether <hi>Paul Appollot,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> or things preſent or things to come, or Life or Death, all are yours and ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods. 2. <hi>Corinth:</hi> 6 16. I will dwell in you and walk in you ſayeth the Lord, and I will be your God, and ye ſhall be my people. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.5. I will never leave you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:179273:12"/>forſake you. 2. Obſerve the Commands to obey them, ſuch as that to love God and His Truths. Intereſt, and people for his ſake, and to believe on the Name of the only begotten Son of God, that ye may have Eternal Life. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3 23, 3 Obſerve Heavenly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and Warnings to receive them, ſuch as theſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 13 24. Strive to enter in at the ſtrait Gate, for many will ſeek to enter in that ſhall not be able. <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.14 Follow peace with all Men and Holieneſs without which no Man ſhall ſee the Lord, whatever his Figure and quality be. 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1 10. Give Diligence to make ſure your Calling and Election: It is a foul Shame that men ſhould content themſelves with a groundleſs Conjecture as to Eternity, whether they be ſaved or damned, they neither know nor care, and yet labour to be ſure of the meaneſt petty Intereſt in the World. 4. Obſerve the Reproofs of the Word to improve them, for the Rod and Reproof gives Wiſdom. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 29 15. God reproves by the Rod by Diſpenſations, By Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by his Spirit and his Word, ſome will have none of his Reproof, which is a black Mark of approaching, Smarting Stroaks. 5. Obſerve the Examples of the word the good Examples for Imitation, and the bad to ſhun them.</p>
            <p>Good Examples. <hi>Enoch</hi> who lived three hundred ſixty five years, and walked with God. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 5, 22, 2. <hi>Abraham</hi> who inſtructed his Children and Houſhold, <hi>Geueſis.</hi> 18.19. 3. <hi>Joſhua</hi> who ſerved God, and his Houſe ſerved God. <hi>Joſhua</hi> 24.15. And it took nothing away from their Gallantry. 4. The Centurion <hi>Cornelius</hi> who was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote Man and feared God and all his houſe. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2. 5ly. <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> valliant for the Truth who rebuilded the Temple in diſpite of Fraud and Force, and was zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for obſerving of the Sabbath. 6. <hi>Mordecas</hi> who ſought not his own but the wealth of his people, <hi>Eſther</hi> 10 3 7ly. <hi>David</hi> who was upright before God, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 18 231 A Man according to Gods own heart. 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 13 14. Who would have the Faithful of the Land to dwell with him, and ſuffered no wicked perſon to be about him <hi>Pſal:</hi> 1.01.</p>
            <p>For bad Examples to ſhun. 1. Beware of <hi>Cains, Geneſis</hi> 4. Who firſt caſt down his Countenance upon his brother, and then ſlew him. 2dly Beware of <hi>Joabs</hi> Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who under the Covert of a courteous Salutation wounded <hi>Amaſa</hi> to Death. 3dly Beware of the Examples of <hi>Pharoh, Haman,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> who were Perſecutors of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and people of God, and all of them made a black Hinder-end. 4tly. Beware of <hi>Abſoloms</hi> Example, who uſed his Politicks to ruine his Father. 2 <hi>Samuel</hi> 15. O! that I were judge ſaid he, I would ſee all Cauſes go right. 5tly. Beware of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Tobias</hi> and <hi>Sanballad,</hi> who under the fair colour of pretended Friendſhip, to concur in building of the Temple, ſought to undermine and ruine the Work of God, Lord think on them ſaid <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> 6 55. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 6. Beware of their Example that prophane the Sabbath againſt whom the Lord threatens to kindle a Fire, that ſhall burn up the places of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſhall not be quenched. 7. beware of <hi>Hiel,</hi> his example who incurred the curſe of God, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6.26. made the People Swear both for the preſent and ſucceeding Generationes, and to confirm their oath, by a Curſe before the Lord, Intimating that he doth utter this not in a Paſſion, but by Divine Inſpiration as appears. 1. <hi>Kings,</hi> 16.34. God would have the Ruins of the City of <hi>Jericho,</hi> to remain as a ſtanding Monument of his Juſtice, that who builds it, ſhall loſe all his Children in the work, the firſt born in the beginning, others in the progreſs, and the youngeſt in the cloſe of it: There is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Divine <hi>predictions and comminations</hi> fulfilled: Hiel, he would choiſe this place for his bulding, not ſo much for his own advantage as out of contempt of the true God and of his threatning, which he deſigned to convince of falſhood by his own experience, and out of an ambitious deſire to advance his own reputation and intereſt: by his ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179273:12"/>he found the truth of Gods Word, and how vain it was to contend with him, he was made an eye witneſs of his Childrens untimely death, as ſome obſerves, ſeveral Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereds of Years after the threatning I warn you all to beware of harbouring any thoughts of Building the <hi>Jericho</hi> of abjured Prelacie, which <hi>Scotland</hi> has been ſo Solemnly and frequently Covenanted and ſworn againſt, a weed that never agreed with this ſoil but alwayes nipt the tender and wholſome plants.</p>
            <p>What loſſes, affronts, and ſmartings of Mind have many, had and ſome of no mean Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count endured in their Perſons end Poſterities who were abetters of that Intereſt, I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſpeak of all which I have obſerved near theſe Fourty Years, I well remember of two of no mean Account, who were among the chief Contrivers of introducing Prelacy, and both of them in their dying had ſevere ſmartings and horrour of Conſcience, one of them, the laſt Sabbaths of his life would ſuffer none of his old Brethren to Preach in his Pulpit, but engaged three honeſt men, who had ſome connivance for the time to Preach in his Pulpite, and took the laſt of the three engaged, that whether he lived or died, he ſhould Preach the third Sabbath, there are living Witneſſes of this at this day, This Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I had from one of the Miniſters, a near Relation of his own, to whom he ackow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, he went over the belly of his Light, and ſaid to one of the Contrivers; we could never ſet up Prelacy in <hi>Scotland</hi> unleſs <hi>B. Sanderſon</hi> ſhould write a Retraction of his Book <hi>De Juramento,</hi> by which he was convinced of the indiſpenſible obligation and binding virtue of the Oath of the Covenant, the Brother he then ſpoke to laid his Head to the wall, and ſat ſilent for a time, yet both of them thortured their Conſciences and comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the deſign I wiſh all may beware of medling with that which has given a Scad, and brunt others, as by Arrows of the mighty, and Coals of Juniper, I would adviſe all, that have leaſure and are diſpoſed without byaſs and prejudice in this point to Read and peruſe what it written by the R. Principals <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Forreſter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jamieſon,</hi> who wrote without conſert, and hardly knew of one anothers ſetting about the work, to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that great Champion for Prelacy Dr. <hi>Monro,</hi> who appeared as if he would give a Defiance to the Armies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but they have turned the Enemy in the Gate, and made him return aſhamed, and it is obſervable, that Mr. <hi>Jamieſon</hi> a blind Man, who in the Worlds account might be thought a ſtripling in compariſon of the great Dr. Yet hath he felled him in the Head, and gone near to cut off the <hi>Golia's</hi> Head, with <hi>Golia's</hi> Sword 8 Beware of their Example who are compared to bruit beaſts, haunting Harlots Houſes, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.7.8.9. ſhall not my Soul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this ſaith the Lord, ſhall I not viſite for theſe things, I dread a vengeance from Heaven, for the ſhameleſs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ounding uncleaneſs of <hi>Scotland. A Whore is a deep pit, who are abhorred of the Lord fall into it, and few or none return to the path of life. Prov.</hi> 1.2.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.14.9. Beware of their Example who has a flying Roll of Curſes broad and long following them to their Houſes <hi>Zechariach.</hi> 5.2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They are called Theives, and falſe Swearers, Oppreſſours are greateſt Theives, and Perjury is a great Sin in <hi>Scotland,</hi> theres an out-cry for frequent impoſing Oaths in Civil Accounts it proves a ſuare to many and occaſions perjury its expected and deſired it be Remeided, we look here and there for cauſes of Diſaſters, and Thuarting and Croſſing of honeſt Deſignes, but let every one look in to their own boſome who is free to caſt a Ston at another, but I will tell you my Mind anent Gods great Controverſie with <hi>Scotland</hi> by three Scriptures which will Anſwer three Objections, <hi>Deut,</hi> 29.24.25. All Nations ſhall ſay wherefore hath he Lord done thus unto this Land, what meaneth the heat of this great Anger, Then men ſhall ſay they have forſaken the Covenant of the Lord God of their Faithers, the Children were bound as <hi>Moſes</hi> tells from the 10 verſe down ward Wives and little Ones, and theſe abſent were under the Oath, what meant the three years
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179273:13"/>famine in the days of <hi>David</hi> 2 <hi>Samuel</hi> 21. It was breach of Covenant with the <hi>Gibeon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> which they obtained by a Cheat, yet was the Lord avanged for the breach of it three hundred years after upon <hi>Sauls</hi> Sons, what meant the Lord to ſtigmatize <hi>Zedekiach,</hi> as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſhould never thrive nor have a day to do well, It was the breach of Covenant he ſwear to <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> The Lord calls it his Covenant his Oath, that he had broken, and he would recompenſe it upon his Head, he did not willingly engage in this Oath <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezar</hi> made him ſwear by God. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.13.</p>
            <p n="10">10ly. Beware of their Example, againſt whom the Lord denounces a wo <hi>Habbac.</hi> 2.15.16. who preſs others to drink to Exceſs, a curſed Cuſtom, for the Lords ſake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear it henceforth.</p>
            <p>Take warning all of you, and warn your Freinds to flee out of the way of Gods Curſe, out of the way of wrath to come, which is the Hell of Hell, If you plump into the pit when you have lien among the flames Millions of Years, It is ay wrath to come, wrath to come, I Charge you all to think on it, and if not, I take Heaven and Earth, the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Stones of this Houſe, and every one witneſs againſt another, and your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences which are as a Thouſand witneſſeſs, I am free of your Blood: It is like when your eye ſtrings are a breaking, you will clear me and condemn your ſelves, Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give you underſtanding in all things, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was as dear to God as <hi>Scotland</hi> is, had the Rulers and People known what belonged to their Peace, and managed Goſpel Oportunities, the City had not been Ranſacted, nor the Streets run with Blood, nor the Temple overthrown, and all come to wrack, O that <hi>Scotland</hi> would take warning, we have our leſſon by their dear bought Experience.</p>
            <p>If there be any that fret, and have Heart riſeing at what is ſaid I am not anxious, for I fear God, and have my Conſcience to bear witneſs, I neither deſigned to Irritate nor Flatter: I have a due deference to Men, in their Reſpective ſphears in Subordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to God, but to no Man the greateſt in Competition with God, who is the alone Judge and Law giver to the Conſcience, who alone. can Save and Deſtroy the Soul: That this God, who is now your witneſs and mine, and will at laſt be your Judge and mine, may by his good Spirit Guid you in the Paths of Righteouſneſs, for his Names ſake, and be your exceeding great, and Eternal reward, Is my Hearty Prayer, And to his Name Father, Son, and Spirit be Eternal Praiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
